<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-02T17:39:58-05:00</updated><id>https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts//</id><title type="html">Eric Brelsford</title><author><name>Eric Brelsford</name></author><entry><title type="html">Google Maps’ areas of interest: update</title><link href="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/maps/nyc/2020/01/02/interesting-areas-update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Maps' areas of interest: update" /><published>2020-01-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/maps/nyc/2020/01/02/interesting-areas-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/maps/nyc/2020/01/02/interesting-areas-update.html">&lt;p&gt;A while back &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts/maps/nyc/2017/08/17/interesting-areas.html&quot;&gt;I looked into&lt;/a&gt; the “areas of interest” Google started putting on their maps. As a refresher, these are the yellowish areas along some streets such as here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/interesting-areas-2019-gmaps.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Via Google Maps&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m curious about these areas in part because I sometimes find them useful when traveling in new cities. If I am wandering around a new place I occasionally look for them on Google Maps as a potential region to explore. Sometimes these areas are very much worth visiting. Usually I am walking a bit aimlessly, stakes are low, and it might not matter much if the areas aren’t specifically what I find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real reason I find myself returning to these areas of interest is that people use them and we don’t fully understand them. When I show Google Maps to students, most do not know what those areas are though they have theories. For example, one recently said they thought the areas were commercial areas. Even relatively tech-adept people seem to assume that these yellowish blobs represent something that objectively exists in the world, the way many of the other markings on Google Maps represent things that exist, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justinobeirne.com/google-goes-green&quot;&gt;vegetated areas&lt;/a&gt; that were recently updated. Areas of interest do not exist. They are not business improvement districts or commercial zones or some other kind of designated area. They have been created algorithmically, and Google has not been clear about the full extent of the data and processes that have been used to generate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All maps are loaded with the perspectives of mapmakers, and a complex map like Google’s is the product of thousands and thousands of decisions and judgements, some more clearly subjective than others. Why not have a legend that describes how areas of interest were generated, or at the very least some indication that they &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; generated? Why not give us a little more agency when choosing whether or not to be influenced by areas of interest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t necessarily dislike them. As I said, I have found them useful at times. But they have been created through an opaque process, and I have a feeling that people use them. Sometimes they are likely used unconsciously, seeing as how the yellow is essentially the mark of a highlighter on the map and will draw people’s eyes. Other times they are used intentionally, but perhaps the person using them does not always know what they are using: arbitrarily drawn map-blobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they’ve changed–a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changes-between-2017-and-2019&quot;&gt;Changes between 2017 and 2019&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I traced every area of interest within NYC &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts/maps/nyc/2017/08/17/interesting-areas.html&quot;&gt;back in 2017&lt;/a&gt;. Out of curiosity I recently overlaid the shapes I created in 2017 on top of Google Maps and saw that seemingly every area has changed in some capacity–some are gone, some are new, most have grown or shrunk in some way. I decided to trace every area of interest in NYC again in order to have a (December) 2019 dataset to compare with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/astoria.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Via Google Maps&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above you can see Google Maps in part of Astoria, Queens (accessed December 2019) with the old areas of interest from 2017 overlaid in brown. This is how many neighborhoods’ areas of interest have changed since 2017–some areas have apparently become less interesting and are no longer highlighted (see, for example, the area around the Museum of the Moving Image in the bottom left) and others have grown or adjusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly here in Brooklyn from Red Hook (now, a bit surprisingly, uninteresting) to Carroll Gardens and Gowanus (both more interesting):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/red-hook.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tweaks are worth examining, but I also want to get an idea of the overall change citywide. Looking at NYC’s NTAs (Neighborhood Tabulation Areas, loosely based on neighborhood shapes), we can see at a glance which neighborhoods lost areas of interest and which gained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/interesting-areas-2019-to-2017.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above, green neighborhoods have more areas of interest in 2019 than they had in 2017, red-pink have fewer areas of interest in 2019 than they had in 2017. In Brooklyn and Queens you can see generally the parts closer to Manhattan got more “interesting”, while the parts further out got less so. Much of Manhattan below Harlem got more interesting, and Harlem got less interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/upper-west-east-harlem.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a diff of the 2017 and 2019 data–orange showing areas that were areas of interest in 2017 but were not in 2019, green showing areas of interest in 2019 that were not in 2017, and gray-blue for areas that did not change. At a glance, you can see that the Upper West Side (left) only gained interesting areas, the Upper East Side (right) gained more than it lost, and Harlem (top) mostly lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/midtown.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above we see a similar diff, here centered around midtown Manhattan. While the losses and gains essentially even out, note that there are dramatically more interesting areas to the south of Times Square and dramatically fewer north and west of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/south-bk.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is the lower half of Brooklyn, generally everything south of Prospect Park. Most of these areas of interest shrank, the notable exceptions being (gentrifying) Sunset Park and Prospect Lefferts, but also 5th Ave in Bay Ridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New York changes constantly, of course, but it would be hard to argue that these places truly got dramatically more or less interesting, not to a point that would warrant changing these shapes. It feels safe to say that these changes are a result of Google tweaking its process for creating these arbitrary shapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;demographics-of-the-2019-areas&quot;&gt;Demographics of the 2019 areas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts/maps/nyc/2017/08/17/interesting-areas.html&quot;&gt;Last time I looked at this data&lt;/a&gt; I used Census data and found that there were some biases in where the areas of interest were located in 2017. Specifically, predominantly black neighborhoods appeared to be less likely to be included in an area of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the 2019 data, areas of interest have not become any less biased. These areas of interest are &lt;strong&gt;even more&lt;/strong&gt; centered on white neighborhoods: 50% of people living in an area of interest are white, which is up from 48.5% in 2017. 42.8% of people citywide identified themselves as white in the Census.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly knowing the above, the areas of interest from 2019 contain &lt;strong&gt;fewer black neighborhoods&lt;/strong&gt;: 16.8% of people living in an area of interest are black, down from 17.5% in 2017. 24.3% of people citywide identified as black in the Census.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also note that there are slightly more asian-identified people living in 2019 areas of interest (14.4%, up from 13.9% in 2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;potential-impacts&quot;&gt;Potential impacts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m curious to know more about how people intentionally use areas of interest–do you use them to explore new places? Are you concerned that Google Maps might be leading you to neighborhoods that aren’t particularly representative of a place if so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do these areas have other impacts, such as on housing prices the way &lt;a href=&quot;https://buffalonews.com/2019/03/17/fruit-belt-fights-for-its-name-over-fears-big-tech-is-erasing-it/&quot;&gt;neighborhood names&lt;/a&gt; have? Might business improvement districts and real estate companies lobby for areas to be marked as interesting, as groups &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/02/technology/google-maps-neighborhood-names.html&quot;&gt;have done&lt;/a&gt; for neighborhoods names? Or might homeowners’ groups, annoyed at tourists visiting their neighborhoods, request removal from areas, as we’ve seen with &lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/why-people-keep-trying-to-erase-the-hollywood-sign-from-1658084644&quot;&gt;the Hollywood sign in LA&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did this type of pressure lead to any of the changes we see above?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my part, I’m going to continue watching these areas and using them (with some caution).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eric Brelsford</name></author><summary type="html">A while back I looked into the “areas of interest” Google started putting on their maps. As a refresher, these are the yellowish areas along some streets such as here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The demographics of Google Maps’ interesting areas</title><link href="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/maps/nyc/2017/08/17/interesting-areas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The demographics of Google Maps' interesting areas" /><published>2017-08-17T01:44:07-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-17T01:44:07-04:00</updated><id>https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/maps/nyc/2017/08/17/interesting-areas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/maps/nyc/2017/08/17/interesting-areas.html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s what happens to New York if you remove the areas that Google Maps says are “uninteresting”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/interesting-area-islands.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Map tiles via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; © OpenStreetMap contributors)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2016 Google started displaying what it calls “areas of interest” on its maps, making portions of the map a slightly-emphasized beige-orange as opposed to the standard gray. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/products/maps/discover-action-around-you-with-updated/&quot;&gt;the company’s press release&lt;/a&gt;, Google says it is using an “algorithmic process” augmented with a “human touch” in more dense areas, but it doesn’t go into detail about what data is being used by these algorithms. As suggested by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.citylab.com/design/2016/08/google-maps-areas-of-interest/493670/&quot;&gt;this CityLab article by Laura Bliss&lt;/a&gt;, there is indeed a likelihood of bias in how Google determines which areas are “of interest” and which are not. One clue toward what kinds of places Google Maps finds interesting comes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://cityobservatory.org/the-most-interesting-neighborhood-in-the-world/&quot;&gt;CityObservatory&lt;/a&gt;, which overlaid storefronts on the map and anecdotally showed that areas of interest are often in places with an abundance of storefronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t noticed them, here are the areas of interest around the East Village:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/interesting-areas-google.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Google doesn’t describe its process for creating these areas any more than, essentially, “algorithms happened and then humans changed things in an unspecified way,” we have to assume that it uses the digital representations of the areas that it has available to it, including web pages it has indexed, map data it has collected and created, and other data such as mobile data on the usage of such places. For example, soon after releasing the areas of interest change on Maps, Google showed just how much information they have about businesses and other venues when it added a feature that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcodesign.com/3065916/google-can-now-tell-you-how-busy-restaurants-are-in-real-time&quot;&gt;shows how busy a place is in real time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean when a corporation starts defining especially subjective phenomena such as the &lt;em&gt;interestingness&lt;/em&gt; of our cities? Then presents its findings as objective facts – areas with firm boundaries? When a map contains ads, doesn’t it have a duty to its ad customers to draw eyes toward those ads?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It certainly does seem that based on Google’s data and financial interests, the areas it chooses to highlight will be skewed toward commercial areas and areas where people have money to spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of the aforementioned articles, I decided to use census data to get a better idea of whether there is a noticeable degree of bias in the way areas of interest are drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-cities-interesting-and-uninteresting&quot;&gt;Two cities: interesting and uninteresting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think of New York as two separate cities, the interesting and uninteresting cities as determined by Google Maps. When we compare these two cities the demographics are significantly different. The census block groups in the areas highlighted by Google Maps are &lt;strong&gt;48.5% white&lt;/strong&gt; while the block groups outside of these areas are only &lt;strong&gt;40.7% white&lt;/strong&gt;. Similarly, the highlighted areas are &lt;strong&gt;17.5% black&lt;/strong&gt; compared to &lt;strong&gt;27.8% black&lt;/strong&gt; outside those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big differences are in the black and white populations, but for completeness’ sake here is the full breakdown. (These labels courtesy the Census Bureau.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;white: 48.5% inside interesting areas, 40.7% outside interesting areas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;black: 17.5% inside, 27.8% outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;asian: 13.9% inside, 13.3% outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;american indian: 0.4% inside, 0.4% outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;native hawaiian: 0.05% inside, 0.03% outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other: 16.1% inside, 14.5% outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two or more: 3.4% inside, 3.1% outside&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few maps of the census blocks with the traced areas of interest overlaid. By percent of population identifying as white:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/aoi-white.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By percent of population identifying as black:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/aoi-black.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we look at household income we see a bit of a skew, though less pronounced than the racial differences: in the interesting city &lt;strong&gt;29%&lt;/strong&gt; of the households have an income of over $100k versus &lt;strong&gt;25%&lt;/strong&gt; in the uninteresting city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Percent of households with an income of $100k or more (green), areas of interest (purple):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ebrelsford.github.io/thoughts/img/aoi-over100k.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does very much seem that the areas of interest in New York are skewed toward more white and affluent parts of the city. I have a feeling that these discrepancies align with other spatial inequities in the city – the areas seem to fall into the more transit-rich parts of the city; which are places that are more likely to be threatened by gentrification; which brings along people who are whiter, more affluent, and likely using the internet and smartphones more. I don’t blame Google for much of this (in New York at least) but it is disturbing seeing these areas enshrined as the “interesting” places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I traced the areas of interest. I did so in &lt;a href=&quot;http://qgis.org/&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt; using QuickMapServices to pull in a Google Maps layer. I traced the layer at a scale of 1:7500, looking for areas of interest in the five boroughs of New York. The scale is important because as you zoom in to a smaller scale the map shows individual buildings as areas of interest. As you zoom out, the areas become more generalized. The scale I chose feels like an appropriate middle ground between very generalized and not generalzed at all. This scale also feels like the scale at which someone might realistically pan around the map – I want to see what the demographics are in the areas that someone will see in these zones while browsing the map in the area around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traced areas certainly were not perfectly traced, but even when they were sometimes they cut through parcels. I decided to find the parcels according to city data that were at least 30 percent within an area of interest. To combine nearby parcels and make the areas fuzzy again, I decided to buffer these parcels by 15 meters. The result, as you will see, is not a perfect copy of the areas of interest, but it is close enough at the scale I am interested in. In order to do demographic analysis with the areas I selected the census block groups that are overlapped by the areas of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eric Brelsford</name></author><summary type="html">Here’s what happens to New York if you remove the areas that Google Maps says are “uninteresting”:</summary></entry></feed>
